Women: A Journal of Liberation Records, 1968-1983
Sophia Smith Collection
Women: A Journal of Liberation records
1968-1983
Women: A Journal of Liberation
MS 319
14 boxes (5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Feminist journal, Feminist collective. This collection consists of correspondence, minutes, research materials, mailing lists, financial records, reader mail, surveys, catalogs, films, legal documents, and most of the printed issues published by the journal. Topics include collectivism, feminism, and journalism.
Women: A Journal of Liberation was founded in Baltimore, Maryland in 1968 by Dee Ann Mims, Donna Keck, Vicki Pollard, and Carmen Arbona in order to provide a national forum for opinions and expression vital to the growing women's liberation movement. Managed by a collective, the journal published its first issue in the fall of 1969. Each issue of the journal focused on a different theme and consisted of invited contributions including articles, news reports, creative writings, and artwork. Some of the earliest contributors to Women were Alix Shulman, Elsa Gidlow, Tillie Olsen, Rita Mae Brown, and Audre Lorde. Originally the collective published the journal five times a year, but quickly reduced the number of issues contained in each volume to four, and then three, in order to meet deadlines more efficiently and to ensure each issue was given the attention it deserved. The intensity of the greater Women's Movement throughout the United States enabled the Collective to attract a large number of subscribers, but by the late 1970s the number of readers decreased rapidly. As a result, due to financial difficulties the journal folded in 1983.
The Women: A Journal of Liberation Records consists of material dating from 1968 to 1983 primarily of documents pertaining to the administrative and editorial side of the publication. Types of material include correspondence, publications, articles, research material for publications, minutes, newsletters, notes, and financial material.
This collection is organized into seven series:
I. HISTORY AND ADMINISTRATION (1968-83, n.d.)
II. FINANCES (1971-83, n.d.)
III. DISTRIBUTION (1970-83, n.d.)
IV. ADVERTISING (1972-80, n.d.)
V. CORRESPONDENCE (1969-83, n.d.)
VI. RESOURCE FILES (1975-82, n.d.)
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Martha Campbell, a representative of the Women: A Journal of Liberation Collective, donated the Records in 1985 after the dissolution of the Collective.
Collectivism -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Feminism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Feminists -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Journalism -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Lesbian feminism -- United States -- History -- Sources; Women journalists -- United States; Women's studies -- History -- 20th century; Women publishers -- United States; Women poets, American -- 20th century; Women authors, American -- 20th century
- SERIES I. HISTORY AND ADMINISTRATION 1968-83, undated, .8 linear ft.
  This series includes documents ranging from the incorporation of the collective and the organization's bylaws to legal records stemming from a law suit with Park Lane Press and a collection of meeting minutes from weekly Executive Board meetings. This series also contains records connected to the Collective's multiple attempts to become a 501 (c)(3) non-profit organization, reprint requests to and from the Collective, various copyright papers, various surveys taken by members of the collective as well as by readers in 1979-80, a few of the resignation letters that came towards the end of the Collective's existence, and articles and press releases concerning the FBI probes into Women: A Journal of Liberation and numerous other "radical" publications during the 1970s.
- SERIES II. FINANCES (1971-83, undated), .8 linear ft.
  This series contains a bounty of material relating to the finances of the collective, including payroll taxes and checkbooks, royalty statements from microfilm, miscellaneous receipts and statements for bills paid throughout the 1970s, and fundraising efforts.
- SERIES III. DISTRIBUTION 1970-83, undated, .8 linear ft.
  This series includes various contact information and mailing lists of numerous national and international publishers and distributors, bulk mailing permits and documentation of "problems" the Collective was having with bulk mailing, and records of distribution with various bookstores or other businesses through correspondence.
- SERIES IV. ADVERTISING 1972-80, undated, .2 linear ft.
  This series contains a mixture of articles that mention and focus on Women, newspaper clippings throughout the years displaying Women's advertising techniques and format, original layouts for such advertisements, and indexes/catalogs that cite Women or contained an advertisement for it. There are also documents related to advertising rates.
- SERIES V. CORRESPONDENCE1969-83, undated, 4.4 linear ft.
  This series contains a wide range of letters to Women from readers, fellow publishers, people the Collective deemed "noteworthy," and everyone in between. While the bulk of the correspondence is from readers requesting more information or a subscription to the collective in the early 1970s, some wrote to contribute artwork or poetry in the hope of being published within Women's pages. Many readers wrote to the Collective to praise its work and provide personal stories for future issues.
- SERIES VI. RESOURCE FILES 1975-82, undated, .2 linear ft.
  This series is a wide-ranging collection of pamphlets and other printed materials from Feminist organizations, publishing houses, and filmmakers the Collective kept on file as reference tools for publication stories or events.
- SERIES VII. WJL ISSUES AND PUBLICATIONS(1969-82, undated), 1 linear ft.
  This series consists of Women: A Journal of Liberation issues the Collective published between 1969 and 1983, ranging from themed issues on "Inherent Nature or Cultural Conditioning?" to the final issue on "Class and Money." After Volume 4, the Collective made the decision to no long publish four issues within a volume, instead only publishing three issues per volume for the remainder to its career. Note: Missing from the Series are the following issues: Volume 1 issue 4, Volume 3 Issue 4, Volume 5 issue 1, Volume 7 issues 1 and 3. The Collective was in contact with University Microfilms to produce microfilm copies of Women that were then purchased by a number of libraries.
- SERIES I. HISTORY AND ADMINISTRATION
  - Incorporation papers 1968-70 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Insurance policy documents 1970s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - By-laws and amendment proposals Winter 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Non-profit information 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - IRS tax exempt attempt 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence
    - L. Paige Marvel 1975-77 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - IRS and WJL's accountant 1975-76 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Legal documents re: WJL v. Park Lane Press law suit 1970-76 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Office procedures and forms 1980-81 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Phone lists undated, 1970-80s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Master forms undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minutes
    - Meetings 1980-81 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Last year of collective 1982-83 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dissolution of collective 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Library of Congress photo duplication service order forms 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Copyright
    - General 1978-82 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Transfers of copyright 1976-78 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - FBI probe: articles and documents 1978-80 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Surveys undated, 1979-80 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Project Adoption and Mothering Project applications 1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photos, memorabilia, and misc. internal correspondence 1976-81 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Reprints
    - Reprint forms undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Permissions WJL requested from various publications 1977-79 (Box 2)
    - Requests to WJL 1969-80 (Box 3-4)
  - Requests pending 1971-83 (Box 5)
    - Refused and cancelled 1970-80 (Box 6)
    - Granted - No Payment 1970-81 (Box 7)
  - Granted - Paid 1970-83 (Box 8)
- SERIES II. FINANCES [See also Oversize Materials at the end of collection]
  - Expense and cash receipts 1976-83 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bank statements 1974-77 (Box 2-3)
  - Bank deposits 1976 (Box 4)
  - Misc. bills paid 1976-78 (Box 5-6)
  - Bills/banking 1982-83 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Taxes
    - Information 1975-77 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Returns 1972 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Payroll taxes 1975 (Box 5)
  - Deductibles 1982-83 (Box 6)
  - IRS communication 1982-1983 (Box 7)
  - Loan agreements 1975-78 (Box 8)
  - Microfilm 1971-83 (Box 9)
  - Fundraising 1981, undated (Box 10)
- SERIES III. DISTRIBUTION
  - Building distribution (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Mailing lists
    - Correspondence 1972-82 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
    - Materials sent from other publishers undated (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - Women's Growth Center 1978 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Bookstore outreach undated (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  - Bulk mailing permits and mailing problems 1982-83 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Distribution-related correspondence 1977-81 (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
  - Accounts receivable 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Eastern News records undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Majority News records undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "Work in Progress" lists of regional distributors, outreach, etc. 1970-82 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- SERIES IV. ADVERTISING
  - General 1972-80 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Rates 1972-80, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Indexes, catalogs, and newspaper articles which mention WJL 1972-77 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- SERIES V. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Subscriptions (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - From other magazines (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "Love Letters from Readers" (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Contributions 1969-78 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - "Noteworthy," 1976-77 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - From individuals 1969-83 (Box 8, Folder 7-22)
- SERIES VI. RESOURCE FILES
  - Committee of Small Magazine Editors and Publishers (COSMEP) newsletters 1979-82 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Feminist organizations, B-W (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Publishing house pamphlets, A-W (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
  - Film resources, C-W (Box 5-8)
  - The Grand Jury Project 1975-76 (Box 9)
  - Lesbian Community Center volunteer switchboard materials circa 1979 (Box 10)
- SERIES VII. WJL ISSUES AND PUBLICATIONS
  - Volume 1 1969-70 (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
  - Volume 2 1970-72 (Box 10, Folder 4-7)
  - Volume 3, issue 1 1972 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Volume 3, issues 2 and 3 1972 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Volume 4 1974-76 (Box 11, Folder 3-6)
  - Volume 5, issues 2 and 3 1977 (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
  - Volume 6 1978-79 (Box 11, Folder 9-11)
  - Volume 7, issue 2 1980 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Volume 8 1981-83 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
  - Other publications 1980-82 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - 1 Checkbook 8 1/1/77-12/29/78 (Box 13)
  - "CASH" booklet with documentation of Loans and A/P 1975-76
  - Checkbook #7 1/2/76-12/15/76
  - Checkbook #6 2/10/75-12/30/75
  - Payroll Registers 1972-75
  - Miscellaneous Account Information
  - Layout for Vol. 8, issue 3 in Oversize box (*Fragile) (Box 14)